Register of the Okhrana records
Hoover Institution Archives
Okhrana records
1883-1917
26001
Hoover Institution Archives
232 manuscript boxes, 86 card file boxes, 6 oversize boxes (194.6 linear feet)
Intelligence reports from agents in the field and the Paris office, dispatches, circulars, headquarters studies, correspondence of revolutionaries, and photographs, relating to activities of Russian revolutionists abroad. Collection is available on microfilm (509 reels). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Russia. Departament politsii. Zagranichnaia agentura (Paris)
Access
Microfilm use only. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1926.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Collection is available on microfilm (509 reels). Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Related Collections
Vladimir A. Burtsev papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Vasilii A. Maklakov papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Pavlovich Martynov writings, Hoover Institution Archives
Boris Nicolaevsky papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Winifred V. Ramplee-Smith collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Russia. Posol'stvo (France) records, Hoover Institution Archives
Russian subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Viktor Nikolaevich Russiian typescript, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
Russian Imperial Secret Police (Okhrana), Paris office.
Scope and Content of Collection
Intelligence reports from agents in the field and the Paris office, dispatches, circulars, headquarters studies, correspondence of revolutionaries, and photographs, relating to activities of Russian revolutionists abroad. Collection is available on microfilm (509 reels).
Russia. Okhrannyi͡a otdi͡elenīi͡a.; Revolutionaries--Russia.; Secret service--Russia.; Socialism--Russia.; Russia--History--Alexander III, 1881-1894.; Russia--History--Nicholas II, 1894-1917.
- I. History of the Okhrana (Boxes 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  The files of the Okhrana office in Paris don't contain statute books giving the legal provision of the agency or printed materials on its establishment and growth. The Special Corps of Gendarmes publications that comprise part of this file, however, give frequent references to pertinent legislation. The collection of annual Vedomost' and Obzor, large volumes covering the period 1887-1901, while intended for the purpose of briefing Okhrana personnel, present the intelligence service by guberniia and illustrate the history of the Okhrana within the empire. The yearly volumes of the Vedomost' (Reports of the Findings of the Imperial Gendarmerie Concerning Offenses Against the State) cover the period from 1887-1897 (with volumes 1892-1894 bound together with the volumes of the Obzor). The Obzor (Review of Important Findings of the Gendarmerie) covers the years 1892-1901.
  Another printed item included under this index is the 1894 Zapiska (a report on the political situation in Poland), which gives Okhrana accounts by guberniia. A short history of the Okhrana abroad is also given in the notes of principal agent Marcel Bittard-Monin, while the small number of documents under this topic serve as a sampling of early operations or as a reference to the laws concerning the service.
  Access
  Available on microfilm reels 1-11
  - Vedomost' doznaniam, proizvodishimsia v zhandarmskikh upravleniakh Imperii po gosudarstvennym prestupleniam, 1887-1897
    - Volume XII, 1887 (Index I, Folder 1)
      Available on microfilm reel 4
    - Volume XIII, 1888 (Index I, Folder 2)
    - Volume XIV, 1889 (Index I, Folder 3)
    - Volume XV, 1890 (Index I, Folder 4)
    - Volume XVI, 1891 (Index I, Folder 5)
    - Volume XVIII, 1894 (Index I, Folder 6)
      Available on microfilm reel 6
    - Volume XIX, 1895 (Index I, Folder 7)
    - Volume XX, 1896 (Index I, Folder 8)
    - Volume XXI, 1897 (Index I, Folder 9)
  - Obzor vaznieishikh doznanii, proizvodivshikhsia v zhandarmskikh upravleniiakh Imperii, po gosudarstvennym prestupleniiam, 1892-1901
    - Volume XVII, 1892-1893 (Index I, Folder 10)
      Available on microfilm reel 10
    - Volume XVIII, 1894 (Index I, Folder 11)
    - Volumes XIX-XX, 1895-1896 (Index I, Folder 12)
      Available on microfilm reel 8
    - Volume XXI, 1897 (Index 1, Folder 13)
    - Volume XXII-XXIII, 1898-1899 (Index I, Folder 14)
      Includes appended alphabetical list of offenders.
    - Volume XXIV, 1900 (Index I, Folder 15)
      Available on microfilm reel 9
    - Volume XXV, 1901 (Index I, Folder 16)
  - Memorandum of the French Minister of the Interior to the Minister of Foreign Affairs, 1887 (Index I, Folder 17)
    Available on microfilm reel 11
  - Background information on French Minister Lockroy, 1873 (Index I, Folder 18)
  - Notes of principal non-Russian agent Marcel Bittard-Monin on the history of the Okhrana in Paris (Index I, Folder 19)
  - News item on a meeting of security chiefs in Petersburg, 1913 July (Index I, Folder 20)
  - References to the basic law of 1896 on the maintenance of Okhrana personnel. Incoming dispatch, 1904 April 20 (Index I, Folder 21)
  - Incoming and circular letters, 1903, 1914 (Index I, Folder 22)
  - Zapiska. Printed report on the political situation in Poland; Okhrana accounts by guberniias, 1895 (Index I, Folder 23)
  - Reference sheet: See IIc for Obshchii sostav upravlenii i chinov otdel'nago korpusa zhandarmov (Index I, Folder 24)
- II. History of Okhrana abroad (Boxes 4-10)
  - a. Paris office (Box 4)
    The earliest document in this series is dated 1886, the year after Petr Ivanovich Rachkovskii was sent to Paris as the representative of the Ministry of Internal Affairs (M.V.D.), or several years after his predecessor Petr Vasil'evich Korvin-Krukovskii (Pierre Newsky) was known to have acted in the Okhrana capacity in France.
    Only the dispatches concerning the growth and responsibilities of the Okhrana office are included in this series. Of particular significance is Rachkovskii's letter to Fragnan, chief of the Paris police, explaining his position and responsibility as chief of the Okhrana mission in Paris. A short draft on the history of the Paris Office and activities prepared by a member of the 1917 commission which terminated the Okhrana abroad is also included.
    - Incoming and outgoing Okhrana dispatches concerning the growth, responsibilities, and management of the Paris office, 1886-1915 (Index IIa, Folder 1)
    - Instructions for collecting military intelligence issued to Manasevich-Manuilov, 1905 (Index IIa, Folder 2)
    - English translation of Rachkovskii's letter to Fragnan, Chief of Police of Paris, explaining his position and responsibilities as Okhrana chief in Paris, 1887 (Index IIa, Folder 3)
    - Introductory draft on the history of the Paris Okhrana, written for publication by a member of the revolutionary investigative commission, 1917 (Index IIa, Folder 4)
      Includes an English translation.
    - Cross-reference sheet (Index IIa, Folder 5)
    - Reference: See IId for letter of instructions for the reorganization of the Paris Agentura, 1913
  - b. European and other outposts (Boxes 4-7)
    - General
      - Outgoing reports #1360 and #1361 on the organization of surveillance according to new principles, 1913 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
        Includes a list of agents by country.
      - Notes giving agents' names and spheres of operation by countries and targets, 1913 (Index IIb, Folder 2)
      - Distribution of deep cover agents of military age by countries, 1914 or 1915 (Index IIb, Folder 3)
      - Incoming and outgoing dispatches, 1906-1910 (Index IIb, Folder 4)
      - Reference: See operational card file by countries in XIIIf(4) (Index IIb, Folder 5)
    - Austria-Hungary
      Proposals were made for the establishment of a separate agentura in Vienna, but no action was taken despite the fact that Russian revolutionaries in Galicia and Trieste (as described in the case of the transfer of large sums of money through a Ljubljana bank) called for some local operations. The only permanent Okhrana agent resident in Vienna was Hans Tuppinger. (See his file in IIIe, Folder 3)
      - Dispatches pertaining to operational tasks and placement of agents, 1906-1914 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
    - Balkan Okhranka
      The Balkan Okhrana was subject to many changes, first with an office in Romania reporting to Odessa, then changing the seat to Sofia and reporting to the Paris Office. The organization developed into a major network, with operatives in all the Balkan countries and Vienna. The documents contained in this collection cover the period from 1886 to 1906, when the Balkan Okhrana ceased as separate unit.
      Available on microfilm reels 11-12
      - Incoming and outgoing dispatches concerning the Balkan Okhranka (Bucharest and Sofia), 1886-1907 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
      - Operational and intelligence reports by Okhranka chief Vladimir Przhestiak (Tsitovskii) from Bucharest, 1902-1903 (Index IIb, Folder 2)
        Available on microfilm reel 12
      - Letters from agent Melas, 1903 (Index IIb, Folder 3)
      - Letters from agent Alfredi in Romania, 1906 (Index IIb, Folder 4)
      - Letter on engaging agents on the Prut river border, 1906 (Index IIb, Folder 5)
      - Names and addreses of four Balkan Okhranka agents (Index IIb, Folder 6)
      - Cross-reference sheet (Index IIb, Folder 7)
    - Germany
      Folder 4 contains only a small portion of the archive of the Berlin Agentura, which existed as a completely separate establishment attached to the imperial consulate from 1900 to 1904, under the direction of Arkadii Garting. He reported directly to Headquarters, but copies of all dispatches were also sent to the Paris Office. Upon liquidation, the archives of the Berlin Agentura were transferred to Paris. See particularly the separate sets of Berlin dispatches of the period in the Outgoing and Incoming volumes under XIIIb(1) and XIIIc(1). The dispatches and notes in this collection pertain to the structure and functioning of the Berlin Agentura, the agent problems after its closure, and a note relating to non-Russian agent work in Germany in 1911. For agent activities in Germany from 1905 to 1914, see folders on agents Neuhaus and Woltz in IIIe, Folder 3, and in VIk.
      - Dispatches concerning the Berlin Agentura and subsequent Okhrana establishment in Germany, 1900-1910 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
      - Letters written by agents or prospective agents after the closing of the Berlin Agentura, 1905-1907 (Index IIb, Folder 2)
      - Reports from an agent named Hengl, 1906-1907 (Index IIb, Folder 3)
      - Note concerning non-Russian agents' work in Germany, 1911 (Index IIb, Folder 4)
      - Reference: See reports of agents Neuhaus and Woltz from 1901-1905 in VIk (Index IIb, Folder 5)
      - Reference: See Garting's first progress report, September 1/14, 1905, in IIa, Folder 1 (Index IIb, Folder 6)
    - Italy
      A separate agentura responsible to the Paris Office was recommended in a 1909 dispatch. No action was taken, despite major operational tasks along the Italian Riviera, where several of the more prosperous revolutionaries had settled. Instead, the Paris Office had a continuous rotation of networks of surveillance agents in the area and operatives in contact with post offices and the police. In 1914, principal agent Invernizzi established a cover firm for Italian Okhrana agents which was administered as a separate team until the Okhrana's termination. (See also the folder in IIIg for the cover firm in Italy and other folders on Invernizzi in IIIe and VIk.)
      - Outgoing dispatch to Headquarters recommending the establishment of an agentura in Italy, 1909 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
      - Intelligence and operational reports submitted to Paris Office by principal agent Invernizzi for his team operating in Italy, 1915 (Index IIb, Folder 2)
    - Scandinavia
      A separate agentura was proposed for Scandinavia in 1906 to investigate arms shipments and clandestine routes. The proposal was not accepted. Agent Sambain's missions to Scandinavia developed some intelligence reporting equivalent to that of a permanent outpost. See XIc(1).
      - Dispatches recommending agentura establishments in Sweden and Norway, 1906 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
    - Switzerland
      Folder 6 contains a small number of documents referring to other European outposts. Two sets of reports from Switzerland reveal that Bogdanov was a resident agent there in 1887 and Dmitriev in 1907-1908, each reporting directly to the Paris Office. Surveillance agents, likewise, were at times resident operatives working closely with local security officers, and at times engaging them as Okhrana agents. See documents on agent Treichler in IIIe, Folder 3.
      - Reports from agent Bogdanov to Chief Rachkovskii in Paris, 1887 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
      - Reports from agent Dmitriev, 1907-1908 (Index IIb, Folder 2)
      - Cross-reference sheet (Index IIb, Folder 3)
    - United States
      At times, a separate outpost was proposed for the United States, but never successfully. The Paris Office was on record as having no adequate coverage for revolutionaries in North America. There was some correspondence with the consular offices in the United States and reports were received from various Russian exiles. Extensive coverage came only after the dispatch of George Patrick to New York in 1912. (See folder on Patrick "Lucy" in IIIf.) The Investigation Commission of 1917 traced 11 Okhrana secret agents in the United States and Canada, according to a draft memo in this folder.
      - Dispatch from Headquarters in St. Petersburg requesting surveillance of revolutionary Govorukhin going to America, 1887 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
      - Okhrana agents in America, a roster compiled by the Investigation Commission, 1917 (Index IIb, Folder 2)
      - Reference: See folder on agent Patrick (Lucy) in IIIf (Index IIb, Folder 3)
    - England
      The first request of Headquarters to dispatch Paris agents to London came in 1890. Throughout the 1890s, there are records of resident secret agents, both British and Russian, but they were essentially only correspondents. At no time until 1912 did there appear anything like a regular outpost. Intelligence requirements were covered by individually engaged agents and by close liaison with Scotland Yard. When Francis Powell became a principal agent in London, the non-Russian agents came under his supervision, while Captains Dolgov and Litvin served at various times as resident case officers for the Russian secret operatives. During World War I, the Okhrana kept a resident in Newcastle to monitor arriving and departing Russian passengers.
      Among the voluminous papers in this collection, Folder 2 contains mostly reports from the 1890s. The names of British people in the service of the Okhrana are in Folder 4. The folders containing agent Powell's dispatches discuss operational problems in London, instructions, monthly statements of accounts, and other materials.
      Available on microfilm reels 12-16
      - Dispatches on the placement of agents in London, 1890-1915 (Index IIb, Folder 1)
      - Reports from London agents, including Farce, on Burtsev, anarchists, Free Russia, and other early revolutionary groups, 1891-1902 (Index IIb, Folder 2)
        Available on microfilm reels 12-14
      - French translation of news items attacking the Okhrana establishment in London, 1914 (Index IIb, Folder 3)
        Available on microfilm reel 14
      - Names of British in the service of the Okhrana, 1914 (Index IIb, Folder 4)
      - Letters from principal agent Francis Powell concerning operational problems in London, 1912 (Index IIb, Folder 5)
      - Letters from Chief Krasil'nikov to case officer Anton Ivanovich Litvin in London, 1915-1916 (Index IIb, Folder 6)
      - Operational and intelligence reports from case officer Litvin in London to Chief Krasil'nikov in Paris
        - 1915 April-September (Index IIb, Folder 7)
        - 1915 October-December (Index IIb, Folder 8)
        - 1916 January-April (Index IIb, Folder 9)
        - 1916 May-November (Index IIb, Folder 10)
      - Financial statements, expense accounts, and receipts pertaining to operations of case officer Litvin in London, 1914-1917 (Index IIb, Folder 11)
        Available on microfilm reel 15
      - London office (Powell and others) monthly statements of accounts, receipts, and bills, 1906-1917
        - 1906-1915 June (Index IIb, Folder 12)
        - 1915 July-December (Index IIb, Folder 13)
        - 1916 (Index IIb, Folder 14)
        - 1917 (Index IIb, Folder 15)
          Available on microfilm reel 16
      - Receipts of individual British agents, 1910-1914 (Index IIb, Folder 16)
      - Letters of instructions from Bittard-Monin to Powell in London, 1914 (Index IIb, Folder 17)
  - c. Official rosters and other publications (Box 7)
    The three volumes filed under this index are the only printed reference materials found in the Okhrana files. They include a book on the structure, administration, and ranks of the Corps of Gendarmes, lists of officers associated with the Okhrana abroad, and a book on rail facilities with a chapter on passenger regulations, including provisions on state security.
    Available on microfilm reels 16-18
    - Obshchii sostav upravelnii i chinov otdel'nago korpusa zhandarmov, St. Petersburg, 1903 July 20 (Index IIc, Folder 1)
    - Ezhegodnik Ministerstva Inostrannykh Del, 1912 (Index IIc, Folder 2)
    - Ukazatel' zheleznodorozhnykh, parokhodnykh i drugikh passazhirskikh soobshchenii, 1910-1911 (Index IIc, Folder 3)
      Available on microfilm reels 17-18
  - d. Reorganization of 1913 (Box 8)
    The radical reorganization in 1913 of the Okhrana abroad affected mostly non-Russian agent networks. Revolutionary counterintelligence under Burtsev was never in a position to expose the identities of Russian secret agents more than one at a time, since these agents operated alone and unknown to each other. Non-Russian agents, however, usually worked in teams, so each one often knew his colleagues. Thus, when any non-Russian agent went "sour," there was the immediate danger he would betray Okhrana agents to the revolutionaries. These non-Russian agents were predominantly mercenary; some earned money from the revolutionaries after they had lost their income from the Okhrana.
    In 1913 Burtsev's office was able to furnish releases to the Paris press listing the names and affiliations of most of the Okhrana's non-Russian agents. Propaganda against the Okhrana abroad led to parliamentary interpellations and general public condemnation of the "ruthless tsarist police" in France, England, Italy, and elsewhere. The Okhrana was forced to reorganize. It made public announcements of complete dissolution and went through the motions of dismissing all non-Russian agents, whether exposed to the public or not.
    In the meantime, however, the Okhrana set up a cover firm in France to absorb the better operatives and set up agents in Italy, England, and elsewhere on a different, more secure administrative footing. The dispatches in this collection contain some exhaustive analysis of the operational problems as interpreted by the Paris Chief Krasil'nikov and comments received from all top officials at Headquarters.
    Available on microfilm reel 19
    - Dispatch from Headquarters discussing problems prior to reorganization, 1913 September (Index IId, Folder 1)
    - Memorandum from Chief Beletskii at Headquarters stating the difficulties of the Paris Okhrana and the need for changes, 1913 September 27 (Index IId, Folder 2)
    - Telegrams and other notes regarding trips and meetings to discuss the reorganization, 1913 September-October (Index IId, Folder 3)
    - Krasil'nikov's analysis of Paris Office investigation units; basis of proposed reorganization, 1913 September 9 (Index IId, Folder 4)
    - Outgoing dispatches to Headquarters on the proposed structure of the reorganized agentura abroad, 1913 August (Index IId, Folder 5)
    - Dispatch from Broetskii with recommendations for a cover firm to replace the direct contracting of investigation agents, 1913 September 18 (Index IId, Folder 6)
    - Letter of instructions from Headquarters on the reorganization, 1913 December 31 (Index IId, Folder 7)
    - Statement signed by twenty Headquarters officials informed about the change in addressing communications to the Paris Okhrana, 1913 October 23 (Index IId, Folder 8)
    - Incoming and outgoing communications pertaining to the reorganization and final accounting, 1913 September - 1914 February (Index IId, Folder 9)
    - Dispatch from Beletskii on changes required in the agentura's investigation structure, 1913 November 23 (Index IId, Folder 10)
    - Letter from agent Henri Durin in response to Sushkov's inquiries regarding dismissal and subsequent rehiring of French agents, 1913 November 17 (Index IId, Folder 11)
    - Reference: See Broetskii's memorandum of October 1913 for estimates of the budget of the reorganized investigation units in IVa (Index IId, Folder 12)
  - e. Wartime Okhrana (Boxes 8-9)
    As noted in many dispatches, Okhrana activities were limited to collecting information on subversives at home and abroad, with a prohibition on collecting military intelligence. When World War I broke out, however, the Okhrana's interests were spontaneously directed to counterespionage against Germany and Austria and soon after to gathering political, economic, sociological, and military information on the Central Powers. When Allied intelligence was centralized in Paris, the Okhrana office there became one of its sources of information, with the Russian military mission in Paris as the channel of communication.
    The original purpose of the Okhrana was neglected during the war due to a lack of personnel and the loss of many communication lines. Many of the non-Russian agents were drafted into Allied military service and all contacts with the experienced detectives in Berlin (Neuhaus) and Vienna (Tuppinger) were terminated. Some of the Russian secret agents were exempted from military service, but they, too, had to be spared for intelligence in connection with the war effort.
    Like many other government and Allied agencies, the Okhrana moved to Bordeaux after the threat of German advance into Paris. Only a skeleton crew with a few files was left at rue de Grenelle. Krasil'nikov's dispatch to Headquarters stated that his office would be at Bordeaux, with outposts remaining in Paris, London, and Bern.
    Of particular interest are Headquarters circulars on the threat of internal revolutions and instructions regarding the Okhrana in wartime. Several issues on account of the war are covered, including positive intelligence tasks and running agents into Germany from Switzerland, the work of the revolutionaries for Germany, and the attempted mutiny of the SS Askold in Toulon.